Guide to the Bella C. Landauer Writings and Reference Collection Ca. 1856 - 1972 (bulk 1926-1950) PR 149
New-York Historical Society
- Series III: Publications
  - Subseries II: Monographs
    - Some Japanese Balloon Prints from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. [New York] The author, 1935. (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Some Terpsichorean Ephemera, from the Collections of Bella C. Landauer at the New-York Historical Society. New York, 1953. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Striking the Right Note in Advertising: Selections from the Music Collection of Bella C. Landauer at the New-York Historical Society. New York: The New-York Historical Society, 1951. (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Upward not Downward!: from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. Privately printed, Christmas 1936. (Box 11, Folder 42)
  - Subseries III: Compilations
    The ten Compilations are quite similar to the monographs, but were not published in the same manner, as the onset of World War II diverted the necessary resources. While these have title pages and illustrations, the illustrations are photostats which are often pasted into the compilations, rather than being commercially bound. Catalog records describe them as "photostat copies of facsimiles." Most of these items have titles such as "[Type of ephemera] in the Bella C. Landauer collection," and were meant to specifically highlight her collection. Landauer distributed many of these compilations to institutions (the New York Public Library, for example, has many of them) and interested individuals (usually collectors.) Most of the compilations found in this collection are extra-illustrated with original ephemera by Landauer. Some Embossed American Tradecards includes a 9 x 11.5 inch gold embossed trade card on coated stock for Crandall and Higgins, piano dealers in Davenport, Iowa. It also includes a hand-written list of "additions" to the collection after the printing of the book. Trivial Washingtoniana is extra-illustrated with (among other things) three colored ribbons with Washington's portrait printed by Mogul Cigarettes.
    - The Indian Does Not Vanish in American Advertising from the Collections of Bella C. Landauer. 1940 (Box 11, Folder 43-44)
    - Pre-frigidaire Ice Ephemera from the Collections of Bella C. Landauer. 1943. (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - Soda Water in the 19th Century from the Bella C. Landauer Collection at the N. Y. Historical Society. [New York: no date]. (Box 11, Folder 46)
    - Some embossed American tradecards. New York: Privately printed at the Harbor Press, 1941. (Box 17, Folder 75)
    - Some music sheets from the Bella C. Landauer tradecard collection at the New York historical society. c. 1940. (Box 17, Folder 76-77)
    - Some terpsichorean tradecards from the Bella C. Landauer collection at the New York historical society. c. 1940. (Box 18, Folder 78)
    - Some tradecards from the Landauer aeronautical collection. c. 1940. (Box 18, Folder 79)
    - Some "Up in a Balloon Songs" from the Collection of Bella C. Landauer. c. 1940. (Box 11, Folder 47)
    - Trivial Washingtoniana from the Collections of Bella C. Landauer. New York: Harbor Press, 1941. (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - When Advertisers Discovered Shakespeare. From the collection of Bella C. Landauer. 1937. (2 parts) (Box 11, Folder 49)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks
  Series IV contains eight bound scrapbooks, in which primary materials are pasted onto pages or were bound as pages themselves into pamphlet binders. Several of these books were bound with embossed titles on their covers, but none have a title page, and they were not published.
  "Advertisements" contains pages from a commercial directory that are randomly bound into a volume. The businesses shown are from New York City and from New England and Boston. Page numbers are random and often repeated, leading to the conclusion that these were removed from separate directories and bound together. Many businesses shown seem to have some connection to printing concerns: engravers, bookbinders, etc. The advertisements are mainly from 1855 and 1856.
  "Aviation University Club exhibition," consists of 11 8 x 10 inch black and white exhibit photographs of some of Landauer's aeronautical collection which was on display at the University Club in New York in 1942. Photographs are individually bound into a pamphlet binding. The scrapbook includes a letter from the editor of Aviation magazine explaining the provenance of the photos, which were given to Landauer by that publication. This scrapbook was disbound and foldered at the time of processing.
  "Old New York" contains forty engravings, lithographs, and chromolithographs of New York scenes, especially downtown buildings and views. The majority of prints are individually bound together into a book with an embossed title. Most were contemporary views printed for D. T. Valentine's Manual between 1858 and 1864, and were lithographed by Major and Knapp; A. Weingartner; Sarony, Major and Knapp; Geo. Hayward; or A. Brown and Co. Scenes include Five Points intersections, uptown intersections (Broadway and 8th Avenue, for example), High Bridge, Central Park, the U.S. Iron Clad Steam-Ship "Roanoke," and Washington Market. Other prints not made for Valentine's are of the American Museum and harbor scenes. Three prints are for Jos. Shannon's Manual, 1863-1868, and were lithographed by W. C. Rogers and Co.
  "Views of Old N.Y." includes sixty prints, which are also individually bound together. This volume includes many plates from books. Prints are either engraved or lithographed, and some are hand colored. The views in this scrapbook are earlier than those found in the previous scrapbook. Many have titles like "New York in 1776" and "Brooklyn (in the olden time)." Other views include the Crystal Palace, City Hall, and a plate that shows a map of the harbor titled "Plan de la Baie de New-York." This scrapbook also includes the front cover, with a photo of the Woolworth Building, of "Men of New York," a September 1925 YMCA periodical.
  "War Songsters" is a small 5 x 8 inch volume holding 55 song lyrics to war songs, most printed on sheets of notepaper with an engraved view at the top. Most songs were lithographed by Charles Magnus, and come from his "500 Illustrated Ballads" series. Several of these sheets are hand colored. Most songs date from the Civil War, although earlier patriotic songs are also included. "The Star Spangled Banner" is present as well as "Sherman's March to the Sea," and "The Soldier's Dream." A few ephemeral pieces are pasted into the front cover.
  "Washington" is a scrapbook containing ephemeral items with images of or relating to George Washington. It includes many engraved portraits and prints from Washington's life, as well as his image on postage stamps, trade cards, and product wrappers.
  There is also an untitled scrapbook is untitled that contains ephemera relating to George Washington. Items include needlepointed slogans, postcards, matchbooks, bookmarks, and programs.
  "George Washington" is a bound scrapbook with an embossed title. In addition to the ephemera items described above, it inccludes a lottery ticket with a presidential signature.
  Scrapbooks are arranged alphabetically.
  - Advertisements, [1856-1860] (Box 12, Folder 50)
  - Aviation University Club exhibition, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 51)
  - Old New York, undated (Box 12, Folder 52)
  - Views of Old New York, undated (Box 12, Folder 53)
  - War Songsters, undated (Box 12, Folder 54)
  - Washington, undated (Box 12, Folder 55)
  - [Washington scrapbook], undated (Box 12, Folder 56)
  - George Washington (Box 22)
- Series V: Reference Works
  Series V contains Landauer's collection of published works by others, used as reference volumes in her Collection Room at the New-York Historical Society. They include monographs, pamphlets, and issues of journals. The majority of the nineteen volumes are extra-illustrated. Landauer sometimes bound items from her collection or correspondence with the author into these volumes (many of which she had bound by the New-York Historical Society or enclosed in cardboard binders.) Extra-illustration often includes items that are related to the author of the books or the subject of the books. Two issues of the Bodleian Library Record include articles about John Johnson, whose large collection of ephemera at Oxford interested and inspired Landauer. A catalog from an exhibition of the John Johnson collection is also included. A typescript list entitled "The Sanctuary of Printing" was sent to Landauer from Johnson. The list seems to be his cataloging system for his ephemera collection. George Phillips' England's Climbing-Boys; a History of the Long Struggle to Abolish Child Labor in Chimney-sweeping, is bound in a volume with several pamphlets about chimney-sweeps, and is extra-illustrated with scraps in the shape of chimney-sweeps, postcards, clippings, and other ephemera bound in. Also includes correspondence, including a valentine from Phillips to Landauer. Most pamphlets were originally housed in pamphlet binders, and were removed from these at the time of processing. Two auction catalogs from Landauer's sales at the Anderson Galleries are treated as monographs.
  The series is divided into two subseries: Journals and Monographs.
  - Subseries I: Journals
    Journals are listed alphabetically by title.
    - The American Book Collector; a Monthly Magazine for Book Lovers. Metuchen, N.J. Vol. 1. No. 7, July 1932. (Box 13, Folder 57)
    - Bodleian Library Record. Oxford: Bodleian Library. Vol VIII, No. 6, June 1972. (Box 13, Folder 58)
    - Bodleian Library Record. Oxford: Bodleian Library. Vol VIII, No. 3, February 1969. (Box 13, Folder 58)
    - Young, James Harvey. "Patent Medicines: The Early Post-Frontier Phase," reprinted from Journal of the Illinois State Historical Society., 1953 (Box 13, Folder 59)
    - Carson, William G.B., "Under the Calcium Lights" (about the American stage in the 1870's), reprinted from Missouri Historical Society Bulletin., 1956 (Box 13, Folder 59)
    - Old-time New England; the Bulletin of the Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities. Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities, Boston, Mass. Vol. XXVI, No. 4, April 1936. (Box 13, Folder 59)
    - Jackson, Holbrook. "A sanctuary of printing: The record room at the University Press, Oxford," An offprint from: Signature: a Quadrimestrial of Typography and Graphic Arts. London, Signature. No. 1, Nov.1935. (Box 13, Folder 60)
  - Subseries II: Monographs
    Monographs are listed in alphabetical order by author. Those monographs listed below with folder numbers are boxed for safety. Those without folder numbers have few extra-illustrations and are shelved with the collection.
    - Anderson Galleries Inc. Books on Typography, New York City, and Currier and Ives Prints from the library of Mrs. Bella C. Landauer, New York City... to be sold... January tenth... New York, Anderson Galleries, 1927. (Box 13, Folder 61)
    - Anderson Galleries Inc. Modern Etchings, English Sporting Prints and Drawings of the Early Continental Schools, the Property of... Mrs. B. C. Landauer, New York and other private owners, to be sold by their order... New York, Anderson Galleries, 1927. (Box 13, Folder 61)
    - Barnhart Brothers and Spindler. Barnharts stock cut catalogue. Chicago: Barnhart Bros. and Spindler, [190-?] (Box 18, Folder 80)
    - Bodleian Library. The John Johnson Collection: Catalogue of an Exhibition. Oxford: Bodleian Library, 1971. (Box 13, Folder 62)
    - Columbia University Libraries. A Catalogue of the Epstean Collection on the History and Science of Photography, and its Applications Especially to the Graphic Arts. New York: Columbia University Press, 1937. (Box 14, Folder 63)
    - Haupt- Lehmann, Hellmut. The Book in America: a History of the Making, the Selling, and the Collecting of Books in the United States. New York: R.R. Bowker Company, 1939. (Box 14, Folder 64)
    - Heal, Ambrose. Old London Bridge Tradesmen's Cards and Tokens. [London]: [s.n.], 1931. (Box 14, Folder 65)
    - C.I. Hood and Co. Hood's Photos of the World: an Unrivalled Collection of 100 Fine Reproductions of Famous Scenes, American and Foreign, First Series. Lowell, Mass.: Hood, [188-?]
    - Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences. Exhibition of Aeronautical Prints, Music, Posters, Book-plates, Dime Novels and Books from the Aeronautical Archives of the Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences. March, 1942, University Club New York. [New York: Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences, 1942]. (Box 15, Folder 66)
    - Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences. Exhibition of Early American Children's Books of Aeronautical Interest, Dime Novels about Flying Machines, Aviation Fiction for Boys and Girls, from the Bella C. Landauer Aeronautical Collection. New York: Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences, 1942.
    - Johnson, John. An Appeal made on Commemoration Day June MCMXXXVIII by John Johnson Printer to the University of Oxford. [Oxford: 1938] (Box 15, Folder 67)
    - Johnson, John. The Sanctuary of Printing. [Oxford: 1936]. (Box 19, Folder 81)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art. I Remember That: an Exhibition of Interiors of a Generation Ago [from] The Index of American Design. [New York: The Museum Press, 1942] (Box 15, Folder 67)
    - Nash, Ray. Some Early American Writing Books and Masters. [Hanover, N.H.?]: H and N, c1943. (Box 15, Folder 68)
    - Phillips, George Lewis. England's Climbing-Boys; a History of the Long Struggle to Abolish Child Labor in Chimney-sweeping. Boston: Baker Library, Harvard Graduate School of Business Administration, 1949. (Box 15, Folder 69)
    - Saunders, Henry S. Whitman Music List. Toronto, Canada: Henry S. Saunders, 1946. (Box 15, Folder 70)
    - Sinel, Joseph. A book of American trade-marks and devices. New York:A. A. Knopf, 1924. (Box 19, Folder 82)
    - Stafford, N. Illustrated Catalogue and Price List of Badges and Checks, Stencils, Seals, Inks, Brushes, etc. etc. [New York] n.d. (Box 15, Folder 71)
    - Vermont Guild of Old Time Crafts and Industries, Inc. A Prospectus Inviting You to Become a Member of The Vermont Guild of Old Time Crafts and Industries. [Weston, Vermont] n.d. (Box 15, Folder 71)
- Series VI: Papers of Aerial Advertising Inc.
  Series VI is a bound volume that contains correspondence and business records relating to Aerial Advertising Inc, a New York City organization that flew airplanes with advertising slogans and messages spelled out in lights on its bottom so as to be seen from below. "The Flying Electric Sign" was its slogan. These records cover the period from 1928 to 1931. Colonel Thatcher T. P. Luquer was a stockholder in and board member of Aerial Advertising Inc., and was the compiler of these records. Correspondence includes letters to Luquer from the president of Aerial Advertising, C. Gilbert Peterson, about the business's prospects, as well as company balance sheets and investment appeals. The volume also includes an Aerial Advertising descriptive catalog 1928. The corporation was dissolved due to bankruptcy in January 1931.
  - Papers of Aerial Advertising Inc., 1928-1931 (Box 15, Folder 72)